<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rubyoffrails | J.Wo]]></title>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/categories/rubyoffrails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-27T15:15:56-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jesse Wolgamott]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RubyOffRails Scholarship for Women]]></title>
    <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2012/07/30/rubyoffrails-scholarship-for-women/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-30T10:35:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2012/07/30/rubyoffrails-scholarship-for-women</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have an opportunity to do something, and I want to do it. Ruby is awesome, and I've been inspired by <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">RailsGirls</a> and <a href="http://kidscodecamp.com/">Kids Code Camp</a>. I want to bridge the gender gap in software development, and this is an initial step for me to do something.</p>

<!-- more -->


<div class="tldr">
    <span class="heading">tl;dr</span> 
I am offering a 100% scholarship to the 6 week RubyOffRails class for up to 5 women software developers. <a href="http://comal.wufoo.com/forms/z7x3p9/">Apply Here</a>
</div>


<p>The <a href="http://rubyoffrails.com">Ruby online training course</a> starts July 31, and I'll keep applications open through <del>August 3rd</del> Thursday Morning, August 2nd. It's a self-paced course, so if you start this week you won't be behind. I'll be granting scholarships to the candidates I feel have the best chance to succeed and will have the most impact. Obviously subjective, but I think this will work. Apply and learn how to be a happy programmer!</p>

<p>So...</p>

<h2>What do you Have to do?</h2>

<ol>
<li>Tell me why you want to learn Ruby?</li>
<li>Tell me how learning Ruby can improve your life</li>
</ol>


<h2>What will you get?</h2>

<ol>
<li>Free access to the Summer RubyOffRails course</li>
<li>Full access to code reviews and office hours. It's a full ticket!</li>
<li>Happiness because you're loving Ruby</li>
</ol>


<h2>Who is this course for?</h2>

<ol>
<li>Developers who have programming experience in a C based language</li>
<li>Ideally programmers who want to learn the fundamentals of Ruby for a career in Rails</li>
<li>Awesome people.</li>
</ol>


<p>You can learn more about the course at <a href="http://rubyoffrails.com">http://rubyoffrails.com</a></p>

<p><a href="http://comal.wufoo.com/forms/z7x3p9/">Apply Here</a>.</p>

<p>UPDATE:<br/>
I was asked what my relationship is to RubyOffRails: I created RubyOffRails in April 2012 and run the course: the video codecasts, discussions, and code reviews are all me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
