<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails, | J.Wo]]></title>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/categories/rails-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-06T10:40:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jesse Wolgamott]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RailsBerry rejected my talk and I am happy about it]]></title>
    <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2013/03/04/railsberry-rejected-my-talk-and-i-am-happy-about-it/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-04T13:12:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2013/03/04/railsberry-rejected-my-talk-and-i-am-happy-about-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I received the greatest email this weekend: RailsBerry had rejected my talk for
their 2013 conference. Normally: another "oh well, they must have found really
great talks to reject mine" and a sigh. Why did I like this rejection email?</p>

<h3>RailsBerry gave me personalized, actionable feedback on making my future submissions better.</h3>

<!-- more -->


<p>First, the details about my talk. I've been teaching <a href="http://rubyoffrails">Ruby off Rails</a>
for a year now. I heart Ruby like a hundred &lt;3s
and think we can show off Ruby more than just showing Rails APIs to developers.</p>

<p>My description of <em>Teaching Ruby without Rails</em></p>

<blockquote><p>What are the essential elements of Ruby that an artisan developer ninja
developer needs to understand before they can see the beauty of Ruby? After all:
there was Ruby before there was Rails; There is Ruby outside of Rails.</p>

<p>Let's cover examples of how to teach Blocks, Send, Class Eval, and Modules to
developers who can develop, but not in Ruby land (yet). And, how these 4
features of Ruby can enlighten Rails and DSLs.</p></blockquote>

<p>In the 'Why should we choose you' section, I added:</p>

<blockquote><p>Honestly? I don't know if you should... I'm a pretty good speaker and people
have been way supportive of my teaching Ruby without the Rails.</p>

<p>How about why you SHOULDN'T choose me, eh?</p>

<ul>
<li>I'm a white male from the US.</li>
<li>I'm not an A-list Ruby developer</li>
<li>I probably won't get someone to buy tickets that wouldn't buy it already</li>
</ul>


<p>However, some things that MAY tip the scales in my favor:</p>

<ul>
<li>I don't use like a billionty meme's in my talks</li>
<li>I'm decently funny and hopefully inspiring</li>
<li>I like &lt;3 tacos, Ruby, and Whiskey.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>I also included a link to my <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=Ucma74yqH6w">Rails Ignite 2012 talk</a>.
I submitted and waited. In late January, I received an email letting me know I
wasn't selected. It was your standard rejection letter.</p>

<p>OK, I thought -- and didn't buy my plane ticket.  I was pretty surprised when
I received the explanation letter on March 3rd. Here
it is:</p>

<h3>The Letter from Michael @ RailsBerry</h3>

<blockquote><p>First of all thank you for taking your time and submitting proposal.
We have received more than 90 and had to select only 7 of them.
It wasn't an easy task and I'd like to give you a little feedback
on why we didn't choose ones that you had submitted.</p>

<p>You've submitted :
  - Teaching Ruby without Rails</p>

<p>  Hmm tough call. You've convinced us that you are a good speaker.
  However the talk proposal lacked the "wow" factor and might not fit into 20
  minutes.</p>

<p>  The talk sounds kind of interesting and I'm sure it can get accepted by plenty
  of conferences.</p></blockquote>

<h3>What I like about the rejection email</h3>

<h5>My talk would be too long</h5>

<p>I missed this completely, 20 minutes is a good speech length, not enough time
to go over what I said I would).</p>

<h4>My talk wouldn't <em>wow</em> people</h4>

<p>True enough, reading back over it. I should have submitted something like
'A Lambda, a Proc, and a Block walk into a bar'... and talk about how their
similarities and differences).</p>

<h4>My speaking qualifications are there</h4>

<p>I'm sending enough information in my submissions to convey I'm decent on stage)</p>

<h3>Suggestions for Conference Organizers</h3>

<p>Feedback like this would be very very awesome to send out to people who asked
to speak at your conferences. Brutal honesty is best: otherwise the speakers
won't know what to change to get better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
