<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | J.Wo]]></title>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-07T10:40:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jesse Wolgamott]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Like Actually Getting Words Onto Paper]]></title>
    <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2015/04/06/writing-like-actually-getting-words-onto-paper/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-06T09:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2015/04/06/writing-like-actually-getting-words-onto-paper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Writing is a series of small burst of rushing water, a thousand words pouring out of me in a very short period of time.</p>

<p>Writing is day dreaming, when no words come at all. The rushing water has stopped, the creek dry and crackling.</p>

<p>Writing is using your own voice and avoiding sounding important or intellectual. Writing is real.</p>

<p>Writing happens in the morning for me. I imagine my brain is still excited about the day in the morning, and like sushi, degrades the further it gets from sleep. I should look into napping. You should find the part of the day you are most creative, and write then. AB test it. Trial and error.</p>

<h3 id="tools">Tools</h3>

<p>Many developers spend days, weeks even, on getting the correct Tool. I have used Pages, Desk.pm, IA Writer, Scrivener, and more authoring tools I can remember. They do not do the work for you, and in general do not make anything easier.</p>

<p>You can also spend days, and weeks, on your toolkit to transfer your words into an ebook format. Or, your site’s marketing website.</p>

<p>But here’s the truth: you are ignoring the part that matters: getting words out of your brain and onto ‘paper’. Stop with the tools, and just write. Use <a href="http://softcover.io/">softcover</a> or <a href="http://leanpub.com/">leanpub</a> - both will create a page for you so you can focus on the writing.</p>

<p>Fiddling with tools instead of writing is wankery distraction.</p>

<h3 id="timeline-of-a-chapter">Timeline of a chapter</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Day 1: write an outline of an article or chapter</li>
  <li>Day 2: fill in the outline</li>
  <li>Day 3: edit the first chapter</li>
  <li>Day 7+: revisit and read with a clean mind. I’ll find that I find I didn’t say all I thought I had said. Or, I’ll find typos clear as day that my mind wouldn’t let me see the previous week.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m currently putting my ideas on writing into action creating Tex Mex
Consulting. Some of my favorite articles:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://blog.texmexconsulting.com/clients-do-not-pay-you-for-the-code/">Clients do not pay you for the code</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.texmexconsulting.com/from-employee-to-freelancer-to-consultant/">From Employee To Freelancer to Consultant</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.texmexconsulting.com/proposals-shitty-to-super-fantastic/">Proposals: shitty to super-fantastic</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
