<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: the-iron-yard | J.Wo]]></title>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/categories/the-iron-yard/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-26T16:18:09-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jesse Wolgamott]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scenes from Seven Cohorts]]></title>
    <link href="http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2016/08/12/scenes-from-seven-cohorts/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-12T09:21:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jessewolgamott.com/blog/2016/08/12/scenes-from-seven-cohorts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two years ago, my first cohort graduated at The Iron Yard in Houston, Texas. 12
students received their diplomas and started their journey, their career, and
their new life.</p>

<p>Five cohorts followed; today my seventh, and final, immersive cohort will
present their final projects and begin the next phase of their live. I look back
and remember:</p>

<!-- more -->

<ul>
  <li>A young student and his mother and grandmother, all dressed up, crying because
of the job offer he received, and never thought he’d have access to this type
of career.</li>
  <li>The mom, who used to develop software, took 6 years off to raise kids, and
received their job offer to rejoin the workforce and support her family.</li>
  <li>The lawyer, who, while crying, thanked me for helping her to realize the dream
she’s had for years.</li>
  <li>The anthropologist who has gone on to multiple jobs, press interviews, and
generally kicks all sorts of ass.</li>
  <li>The musician who graduated, brought his friends to The Iron Yard, and all
started a company together.</li>
  <li>The waiter, who felt stuck in a dead end career, giving meetup talks and
negotiating better jobs.</li>
  <li>The veteran, coming back to the US after Afghanistan, and starting a career.</li>
  <li>The scientist, always pushing herself to do more, learn more, and be more.
Watching her build up the nerve to negotiate her salary/benefits, not for
herself, but because more women should.</li>
  <li>The star of the course, developing open source software and sharing
interesting things he finds on the internet with me. (I’m learning from him)</li>
  <li>My TA, coming back and sharing her time with students, one-on-one, and helping
run RailsGirls and helping even more people.</li>
  <li>And so many others…</li>
</ul>

<p>I want to thank you all; I was a smart part of your journey, and you were a big
part of mine.</p>

<p><img src="/images/jwo-tiy.jpg" alt="jwo-tiy" /></p>

<h2 id="something-that-actually-matters">Something that actually matters</h2>
<p>Overall, I’ve graduated nearly 100 students over 7 cohorts. I started at
the Iron Yard in 2014 with a healthy skepticism on code-schools – I thought,
‘hey JWo, you’ll be able to help with things you care deeply about.’ Namely: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Helping to solve the diversity problem in Tech.</li>
  <li>Teaching kids how to code.</li>
</ul>

<p>Being a part of something that actually matters to you is an experience I highly
recommend. I spent the first 18 years of my career trading my time and ability
to tell computers what to do in exchange for money. You know, as you do.</p>

<p>But being able to do so AND help people AND align with your core desires – it’s
an emotional experience I cannot fully describe. </p>

<p>I’m proud of what I’ve done at The Iron Yard in Houston, believe whole-heartily
in TIY’s ability to affect real and lasting change for people, and want to
expand the scope of the people I can help.</p>

<h2 id="add-some-zeroes-to-that-number">Add some zeroes to that number</h2>

<p>On Monday, I’ll start a new position at The Iron Yard as the Director of
Back-End Engineering. I’ll lead the effort to wrangle the curriculum for the
back-end stacks we teach at TIY nationally: Rails, .NET, Java, and Python, as
well as help develop curriculum for non-immersive courses.</p>

<p>I hope to be able to expand the people we can help, including those who cannot
take a 12 week immersive code school. Additionally, I’m excited to experiment
with other formats and show off the technology TIY’s internal tech team has
built. So Excite. Such potential. Very future.</p>

<p>My goal: as bittersweet as it is to finish leading 15 students on a twelve week
journey, I hope to add some zeroes to that number. At 20 campuses (currently),
The Iron Yard is the largest codeschool in the country; helping instructors help
students has the potential to change even more lives.</p>

<h2 id="excite">Excite</h2>

<p>I’m like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/ron.gif" alt="images" /></p>

<p>No really, see:</p>

<p><img src="/images/jwo-dance.gif" alt="images" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
